Guide to the Sam Winn Papers WAG.203
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sam Winn Papers
1907-1978, (Bulk 1950-1978)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Winn, Sam.
WAG.203
7 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Sam Winn (1903-1978) was an activist, an organizer and a business agent (Local 490, Paperhangers) in District Council 9 of the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. He was also a militant member of several rank and file groups within the District and the Local, fighting for democratic rights and improved working conditions for members and against corruption. He challenged the District leadership in several election campaigns and through his writing in rank and file newsletters; they retaliated by bring legal proceedings against Winn and his associates. The collection includes District minutes, District and local union by-laws and agreements, correspondence, convention proceedings, publicity material, clippings and legal documents. NOTE: This collection is stored offsite, and advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The papers of Sam Winn were donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by his son, Peter Winn, in March 1995.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: This collection is stored offsite, and advance notice is required for use.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sam Winn was born Samuel Winokur in rural western Ukraine in 1903. At the age of nine he moved with his family to the town of Lyubar (between Kiev and Lvov), where he received a rudimentary education. His father emigrated to the United States with the intention of saving money so the rest of the family could follow. The plan for emigration was interrupted by World War I and young Sam began to work as a rural laborer in the harvests and soon developed strong leadership skills. In 1919, with the Ukraine ravaged by civil war and anti-Semitic pogroms, he led a group of immigrants from Lyubar to Warsaw, where he was able to make contact with his father. With the help of the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society (H.I.A.S.), Sam and his family finally traveled to the United States.
Winn lived briefly in New York City, on the Lower East Side, before joining his family in Boston, where he went to high school. He eventually became an apprentice paperhanger and met his wife-to-be, Esther Berowitz, herself an immigrant from the Ukraine and an activist in the shoe-workers union. It was in Boston that Sam became politically aware and a labor activist, first as a member of Paperhangers= Local Union 258 and then as an organizer for the United Textile Workers in northern New England. When the Depression hit, he became active in the Unemployed Councils, was an organizer of the 1931 Hunger March in the Boston area and later worked for the Congress of Industrial Organizations (C.I.O.)
In 1935, Winn moved to New York to help the effort led by Louis Weinstock to gain control of the International Brotherhood of Painters' District Council 9 from the racketeer-linked AZausner Gang.@ For the next four decades, Sam Winn was a leader of the Rank and File Painters= Club of DC 9; he edited club the newspaper and wrote many of its flyers and leaflets. During the Weinstock era, he was a member of the leadership group within DC 9, a frequent delegate to national conventions (including the infamous 1937 Buffalo General Assembly, where he was an outspoken challenger of the national leadership) and an organizer for the war effort during World War II. During Martin Rarback=s tenure as District 9 secretary-treasurer (1947-1966), Winn was an outspoken leader of the opposition for two decades. He played an important role in Rarback=s ouster and trial, and was a frequent target of Rarback=s attacks, which failed to oust Winn in 1953, but succeeded in a trumped-up case in 1962. Winn was also an important supporter of Frank Schonfeld, reform leader in DC 9, and a key organizer of the alliance that brought Schonfeld victory over Rarback and sustained him in office. Sam Winn continued to play an active role in the life of DC 9 after the Schonfeld era as a leader of the opposition to District secretary-treasurer James Bishop.
For over four decades, Sam Winn was also a leading member of Local 490, the Paperhangers= Local within DC 9. He was business agent for two decades (beginning in 1942) and at other times chair, council delegate and trustee of Local 490, as well as the local union=s delegate to the New York Central Trades Council and to numerous state, regional and national meetings of the Brotherhood and of the AFL-CIO. Winn also played a leading role in the creation of the Eastern Seaboard Paperhangers Conference during the 1950s, serving as its Secretary. One of its goals was the establishment of a Paperhangers Department within the Brotherhood, with Winn as its likely head. Before that could happen, DC 9 president Martin Rarback was able to bring him up on charges, oust Winn as business agent and deprive him of his union rights. Although this case was reversed on judicial appeal, it upset the trajectory of Winn's career as a union officer. He returned to work as a paperhanger, but suffered a vocational injury that made it difficult for him to work.
Sam Winn retired from work in 1968, but remained an active member of Local 490 and DC 9 until his death in 1978. He devoted much of the last decade of his life to establishing a credit union within DC 9, and served as its Treasurer until his death from cancer at age 75.
Scope and Content Note
The Sam Winn papers include correspondence, DC 9 and local union minutes, by-laws and resolutions, election materials, rank and file flyers and newspapers, convention materials, collective bargaining agreements, credit union and unemployment insurance materials, information on the painting industry, the Joint Industry Board (JIB), internal trial and disciplinary materials, including charges filed against various contractors, materials on the District Council Secretary-Treasurers: Martin Rarbach, Frank Schonfeld, and James Bishop; on the trusteeships imposed on the District Council by the International, and the amalgamation of locals that took place in the 1970s. Additional materials include documentation of the expulsion of Communist Party members, as well as documents from the myriad legal cases that developed out of rank and file activities, as well as other legal challenges within the District Council.
NOTE: This collection is stored offsite, and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into three series:
Missing Title
I, Minutes, 1940s-1977
II, Subject Files, 1907-1978
III, Legal Files, 1940s-1978
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Blum Papers (Wagner 100)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Painters District Council 9, Records (Wagner 150.)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Painters District Council 9, Trusteeship Records (Wagner 149)
Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America, Local 490, Records (Wagner 42).
Vertical Files: Benson, Herman, “Insurgency and Reform in the Painters, 1960-1987” (Author File).
Daniel French Papers (Wagner 101)
Burton Hall Papers (Wagner 87)
Frank Schonfeld Papers (Wagner 27)
Newsletters.; Minutes (administrative records); Correspondence.; New York (N.Y.); Painters, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Clippings (information artifacts); Labor disputes -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor union democracy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Fliers (printed matter); Collective labor agreements -- Painters, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Legal documents.; Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions and communism.; Winn, Sam.; Schonfeld, Frank; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 490 (New York, N.Y.); United Rank and File Painters Social Clubs of Greater New York; Rarback, Martin; Bishop, James; French, Daniel, 1908-
- Series I: Minutes, 1940s-1977.
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9) (I), 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9) (II), 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes: New York District Council (IBPAT, DC 9), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1907-1978.
  - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), Building and Construction Trades Department: 13th National Legislative Conference, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO, Building and Construction Trades Department: National Jobs Conference, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Berlin, Louis, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bishop, James, 1970-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Building Trades: Civil Rights Issues, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Calden, Eugene, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1937-1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Conferences: International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades (IBPAT), New York State, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Conferences: Paperhangers 1st Eastern Seaboard Conference, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Conferences: Paperhangers 2nd Eastern Seaboard Conference, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Conferences: Paperhangers 3rd Eastern Seaboard Conference, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Conferences: Paperhangers 4th Eastern Seaboard Conference, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Conferences: Paperhangers 5th Eastern Seaboard Conference, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Conferences: Paperhangers 5th Eastern Seaboard Conference, Sam Winn Speeches and Reports, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Contractors and Employers, 1950-1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Datebook (excerpt), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Dinners, Balls, and Banquets, Undated, 1941-1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Election Materials, Undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Election Materials, 1949-1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Election Materials: Daniel French, 1950, 1967, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Election Materials: Locals 51, 442, 454, Undated, 1951-1970 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Election Materials: Locals 848, 874, 892, 905, Undated, 1953, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Election Materials: Independent Paperhangers of Local 490, [1970] (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Finances, 1957-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Finances: IBPAT, DC 9 and Local 490 Audits, 1950-1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Finances: IBPAT, DC 9 and Local 490 Audits, 1958-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Finances: Work Tax, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - French, Daniel, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - IBPAT: 15th General Assembly, Buffalo, NY, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - IBPAT: 19th General Convention, Seattle, WA, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - IBPAT: 20th General Convention, Cleveland, OH, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - IBPAT: 21st General Convention, Minneapolis, MN, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - IBPAT: 23rd General Convention, Los Angeles, CA, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - IBPAT: Charges against Employers, Undated, 1957, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - IBPAT: Charges against Paperhangers, 1949-1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - IBPAT: Proposed Amendments to the Constitution, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - IBPAT: Research Department, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - IBPAT: Wage Claims, 1955-1967 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: General, Undated, 1948, 1958-1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Amalgamation Issues, 1972, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Arbitrations and Agreements, 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Arbitrations and Agreements, 1945-1967 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: By-Laws, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: By-Laws, 1949-1959 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: By-Laws, 1964, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: By-Laws, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: By-Laws, Locals 490, 905, 1959-1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Communist Party Members Expulsion, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Facts and Figures Bulletin, Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Newsletters and Clippings, Undated, 1966-1968, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Open Letters to Membership, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Protests and Petitions, 1956-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Referendum Votes, 1945, 1950-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Special Painters' Victory Drive, Program, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Special Trusteeship, 1967-1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - IBPAT, DC 9: Trial Board, 1953-1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - IBPAT, DC 36, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - IBPAT, Local 454, Undated, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - IBPAT, Local 490, 1907, 1959-1978 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - IBPAT, Local 490: Correspondence, Undated, 1960-1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - IBPAT, Local 490: Membership List, Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - IBPAT, Local 490: Newsletter, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - IBPAT, Local 490: Paperhangers Apprentice Record, 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - IBPAT, Local 490: Progressive Newsletter, Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - IBPAT, Local 490: Resolutions, Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - IBPAT, Local 490: Work Logs and Memos, 1952-1958 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - IBPAT, Local 848, Undated, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - IBPAT, Local 892, Undated, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - IBPAT, Local 892: Progressive Group, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - IBPAT, Local 905: By-Laws, Rank and File Newsletter, Undated, 1964-1968 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - IBPAT, Local 1011, 1958, 1961, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Joint Industry Board, 1952-1960 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Joint Industry Board: Audit Reports, 1957-1962 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Jurisdiction Claims, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Kushner, Max, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Labor Management Reporting and Disclosure Act, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - League of Union Painters: The Paint Pot, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Mailing Lists, Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Membership Rights Club, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - New York State Department of Labor: Unemployment Insurance Referee, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - New York State Painters Jurisdictional Booklet, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Organizing: Manual and Materials, Undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Painters' Free Press: Newsletters and Bulletins, 1961-1978 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Painting Industry Insurance and Pension Funds, 1949-1978 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Pricing Committees, 1956-1965 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Publicity: Broadsides, 1949-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Publicity: Flyers, 1934, 1943-1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publicity: Press Releases, 1949-1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Publicity: Local 261: Leaflets, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Publicity: Local 490: Broadsides, Undated, 1954-1970 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Publicity: Local 490: Leaflets and Flyers, Undated, 1948-1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Publicity: Local 499: Leaflet, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Rank and File Newsletters, 1948-1974 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Rarback, Martin, 1949-1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Realty Maintenance Company, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Richman, Harry, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Safety Issues: Building Trades, Undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Schonfeld, Frank, 1964-1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Shop Stewards, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Siegel, Harry, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Smith Act, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Strikes and Work Stoppages, 1962, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Strikes: DC 9 Strike Bulletin, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Strikes: Picketing, Undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 376: Appeal (printed), 1926 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - United Rank and File Painters' Clubs, Undated, 1950-1953 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - United States Department of Labor: Labor Organization Information Report, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Wage Rates: Building Trades, 1967-1971 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Webman, Isadore, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Weinstock, Louis, 1940s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Winn, Sam: Job Notes and Reports, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Winn, Sam: Notes (1 of 2), Undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Winn, Sam: Notes (2 of 2), Undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - World Federation of Trade Unions: 2nd World Congress, Supplementary Documents, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Writings (drafts of articles), Undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Yiddish Flyers, Clippings and Draft Article, Undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Series III: Legal Files, 1940s-1978.
  - Arnold, Frank, v. IBPAT, DC 9, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Briefs, Correspondence, etc., 1940s (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Briefs, Correspondence, etc., 1950s (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Briefs, Correspondence, etc., 1960-1962 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Briefs, Correspondence, etc., 1963-1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1962 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - French, Daniel: Various Cases, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - French v. Association of Master Painters and Decorators of the City of New York and Rarback (No. 3462-1961) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - French, et al. v. Rarback, et al., New York State Supreme Court (No. 2572-1961) (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - French, Caputo, Levine Trial: Misc., 1961 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - French, Levine, and Winn v. Caputo (No. 941/1962) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - IBPAT (Raftery and Wolford) v. IBPAT, DC 9 (Levy and Bishop), 1977 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Kushner v. Rarback et al. (no. 7889-1961) (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Rarback, Martin, et al.: Indictment, ca.1965 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Rarback v. IBPAT, Local 490, Jun 15, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Rarback v. IBPAT, Local 490, Jul 13, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Rarback v. IBPAT, Local 490, Sep 6, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Rarback v. IBPAT, Local 490, Sep 13, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Rarback v. IBPAT, Local 490, Sep 15, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Rarback v. IBPAT, Local 490, Sep 16, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Rarback v. IBPAT, Local 490, Oct 18, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Schonfeld, Frank: Charges against, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Schonfeld v. Penza et al. 72 Civ. 2837Schwartz, et al.. v. Levy 72 Civ. 4971, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Schonfeld v. Raftery, 67 Civ. 1361, Jun 16, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Schonfeld and Winn: Incomplete Trial Record, Undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Surowitz, Solomon: Counselor at Law, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Topp, Edward: Trial, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Wedl, Frank: Trial, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Winn, Sam: Charges against, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Winn, Sam: Legal Materials, 1959-1963 (Box 7, Folder 30)